Hello and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrdan.
And we're gonna be continuing to go
through math skills to ACE chemistry.
Remember, this playlist is all
about trying to learn all your
basic chemistry, math skills to help
you pass your chemistry courses.
And today we're gonna be looking
at the order of operations.
Which is something you learned probably
back in grade school a long time ago,
but we're gonna go through the different
order of operations, how to look at them
and how to round them when it comes to
different mathematical formulas, which
is really commonly seen, whether it's in
general chemistry one or in introductory
chemistry, when you are using different
formulas or parentheses, Sometimes you'll
see it commonly in dimensional analysis
just doing basic multiplication and
division, but you're going to be seeing it
in using a lot of different applications.
So what is it, well that's going
all back to what we remember from
a long time ago, which is PEMDAS.
So, we're gonna be looking into that
if, and if you can kind of really
remember from a long time ago what
was PEMDAS and you can can remember
that little saying, "Please Excuse My
Dear Aunt Sally", which is all about.
All the different operations you can
do with math, whether it would be
parentheses, exponents, multiplication,
division, addition, subtraction.
You saw all, all these different things,
and that's what we're gonna be looking
at as we are going through this and
going through the steps of PEMDAS,
which as you read, that's saying from
left to right, that's the order that
you will do operations in, meaning
that we first, we do parentheses first.
Then exponents, then multiplication, then
division, then addition, then subtraction.
So throughout this video, we're gonna go
through many different examples, going
over the significant rules of this.
And how you can round these answers
so that way you're getting the correct
answers in your chemistry course
when you are using them all the time.
All right?
So stay tuned for different examples
and please hit that like and subscribe
button to help support the channel.
Thank you.
So, in our first example of this
problem, what we're gonna be doing is
something that has multiple operations.
So, as I said before, what we're
going to be really looking at here is
try to look at a couple little tips.
First thing it says is parentheses.
Looking at the problem, it says,
18.7 divided by 1.38 plus 5.1.
The key is whenever you see fractions,
the first thing I would always
recommend to do is assume the following.
So we have two parts of a fraction and
we'll have a video in fractions later.
But you have your numerator,
which is on top, and then your
denominator, which is on bottom.
What I always like to do for myself is
assume that these are always both in
parentheses, so that means you carry out
the operations on top and the operations
on bottom before proceeding to do the
fraction, because whenever you have a
fraction, That represents a division.
Okay?
So that is just that you're
dividing and you're going to
carry that out like normal.
However, we need to make sure we
do the other operations first.
So the bottom right, you see that
addition, it's in parentheses.
We have to carry that out first.
So let's go through and do
that part of the problem.
So 1.38 plus 5.1.
When you plug all that into
your calculator, you're
gonna see you will get 6.48.
Now we do the next step.
So we did addition, we
did parentheses first.
Now we have division
between top and bottom.
We will carry out the 18.7
divided by 6.48 to get 2.8858.
Is that the right way to show the answer?
Well, this is where we're going to go
through all the different forms of how
to round, and one of the things when it
comes to rounding is this takes practice.
So we need to learn our
rounding with sig figs again.
So this is something
that keeps coming back.
So definitely watch the earlier
videos in the series about rounding.
So you know the basics.
Now we're gonna apply it to
different orders or operation.
When we are going through here, the
idea is that with multiplication
division, the final answer must be
rounded to the same number of sig figs
as the number with the fewest sig figs.
So when we are going through this, we
need to always figure out what the fewest
number of sig figs are, multiplication
division is, the easier of the two rules.
So when we are looking for this, what
we are going to be seeing is that, all
right, if I have this example down here
we have 4.50, which if you remember
how to count those sig figs, right?
We have 1, 2, 3.
So we have three sig figs, and on the
right hand number we have one two sig
figs, meaning that our final answer
for, so when we solve this is going
to have two significant figures.
Now there's another part of this
rule that we gotta keep in mind too,
and that has to do with the units.
Now, the units are all about when
multiplying, dividing, is that
you're essentially taking, you're
combining the units to either
find the product or the quotient.
So after either you multiply it or
you divide it, and you're taking that
product or quotient of those original
units, what does that even mean?
So, with this one down here,
we're multiplying these.
So, if we're taking the product,
So, if I have centimeter times
centimeter, what's gonna be my product?
Well, think of if you're
measuring a room, right?
If you are measuring an apartment,
it's always reported in like
square foot or things like that.
Well, this time centimeter times
centimeter is square centimeter.
And that's what we're gonna have.
So this would be centimeter
squared will be our units,
and then we'll carry this out.
So 4.50 times 2.5.
It's going to give you a number
of 11.25 centimeter squared.
However, what we're going
to have to do is round this.
So we said two sig figs is what we need.
So we'll round this to the
second sig fig spot, right?
So it's 1, 2, 3, 4, around
that to the second spot.
Usually we just underline
it once to show that.
Meaning that our final answer is
going to be 11 centimeters squared
or our final answer in this problem.
So that's how you do for
multiplication division.
Let's go to the next one is, as you
can see, we have the following problem.
This time is division.
So a couple things we gotta do first.
First, let's count our number as sig figs.
So we have 1, 2, 3, sig figs.
To the next one.
We have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 sig figs.
So we have that.
Now the idea was, is that
you bring down whatever the
lowest number of sig figs was.
Three is our lowest amount.
So what we are going to do here is
our final answer when we solve for
it, is going to have three significant
figures in the final answer.
Now, what about the units?
Well, let's think about
how this is gonna be.
It has to be the quotient of the
units because we are dividing here.
So one way that you can show this
problem is really gonna be helpful
for dimensional analysis and unit
conversion is let's rewrite the problem.
So we have 3.0 grams.
All over 1.5 0 0 0 milliliters.
And as you can see, we're writing
this in the form of a fraction.
So when you are showing this, well, all
we have to do is simplify the fraction.
So if we do that right, three
divided by 1.5, and you can
think like, oh, that's just two.
Right, but we need to make sure
we put it S three sig figs.
So when you do that, right, so
it'll be 2.00 and that'll be
grams all over one milliliter.
Or the way you can also show that is
2.00 grams over milliliters, and you
can write that sideways just like that.
And that's how we can show
a different derived unit.
Which can be very helpful.
And this is something that represents
density, which is going to be one of
your most common things that you're
gonna be using when you do general
chemistry labs, especially probably
around those first couple weeks.
A lab, you're gonna commonly use
density to go from mass to volume,
or whether it's for liquids or
for, for different solids as well.
All right, so that's for
multiplication division.
Let's go on to the next one
for addition and subtraction.
Okay.
So for addition and subtraction,
the final answer has to be the same
number of decimal places as the
number with the fewest decimal places.
And you're probably reading that.
Like what?
Well, when we are going through
this, we're gonna be counting the
decimals, meaning how many numbers
there are past that point, whichever
has the lowest number of decimals.
Is what's going to be actually
defining our number of sig figs.
So the other thing to keep in mind
too is when we have units, you
can only do addition subtraction
for things with the same units.
So if we, being that we are taking
measurements very often in lab,
if we're doing grams, right?
So masses, they have to
be all the same mass.
Same exact unit, same prefix as well.
So when we do unit conversion
videos, prefixes matter.
They also have to be the same
volumes and things like that.
So multiplication division, you
can combine whatever you want.
But when it comes to addition,
subtraction, they have to be the same.
So when we do our first example
here, we see that we have
0.0456 meters plus 1.14 meters.
Plus 0.00148 meters.
And in this problem, they
are all the same unit.
They're all meters.
So we can add this up.
Now, earlier I mentioned that
we have to make sure that we are
counting how many significant values
are after the decimal, and that's
what's going to affect our rounding.
So for this first number, right, we
have three values past the decimal.
This next one, we have two sig figs after.
Even though this entire number
keep in mind is three sig figs,
so the whole number's still three.
But for addition, we only
worry about the decimals.
So there's two of them.
In the next value, there are
three cig figs after the decimal.
So when we are doing these
calculations, what are we gonna
have for our final answer?
So we're gonna have two sig figs after
the decimal for our final answer.
Okay?
So keep that in mind.
This is what is going
to be affecting that.
So let's rewrite the problem.
So it looks like more like
a normal addition problem.
You can plug this into your
calculator, being that most likely
in your gen chem class, you will
be allowed to use a calculator.
Very rarely does a teacher say no.
So we're gonna write these out
so that way you can see all the
decimals lined up, just like how
you used to do back in grade school.
So we'll line up the decimal, we'll line
up our units just like this, and we are
going to be adding up all those values.
So as we mentioned, we're
gonna have two decimal places.
So this is going to be rounding to
right here where that little line is.
So when we add all this up, so if
you plug this in your calculator,
you're going to get 1.18708, and
we're going to be rounding that to
that second decimal place, meaning
that eight is next to seven.
And if you remember from our previous
video, we're gonna round up as a result.
So being that we are rounding up
here, this is going to be equal.
To 1.19 meters for our final answer here.
Let's go on to the next part.
Alright, now let's put it all together.
Let's go back to the example from earlier.
So going back to PDOs, meaning please
excuse my dear Aunt Sally, when
we are doing combined operations
is when things can get a little
confusing and a little hard, but
with patience and some little tips.
This can be very easy to do.
So first rule for this is you wait
until the end to round your problem.
Do it at the very last step as you're
going through your steps, whether it's
parentheses, exponents, multiplication,
division, each operation you do underline
the significant value or that you should,
you should be rounding that step too.
So meaning when we go through,
let's say a multiplication step.
And that's first we're gonna put a
little line to say, okay, this should
be two sig figs, or three, so let's
go through the first problem and
show how we would do that problem
again, but with proper rounding.
So the first thing I said was, is
make sure you pretend at the top and
bottom or in the proper parentheses.
So we are gonna first do the bottom.
So this is gonna be 18.7.
Divided by 1.38 plus that 5.1.
So when we do the bottom, we
can see that we have how many
sig figs we got on each part.
We have one, two on the left
and only one on the right.
So that means we are going to
have just one decimal place
after this edition operation.
So when we write that down
and have our number here, We
are going to underline that.
So we have 6.48.
We're gonna underline one after for
our notes for ourselves for later,
so that way we are keeping track.
Now in our next part, which is, so we
did addition first, add in parentheses.
Now we are going to divide,
right, so multiply divide.
So when we do this, 18.7 divided by 6.48.
What we will get is our answer that we
had before, so 2.8858, and when we divide,
we take the lowest number of sig figs.
We can see the both parts of this.
How?
What would we have?
Well, we have three sig figs on the top
right, so this will go to the third spot.
And being that the number on the bottom
would have been rounded to two sig figs.
We have three and then
two from our operation.
So when we are doing that, that
the, that denominator is going
to be affecting our rounding.
So we'll take this, we'll take that eight,
round it up, and our final answer is going
to be 2.9, showing those two sig figs.
And as you're kind of going
through these, if there's units
involved, we would keep them.
Oops.
And we would put them in
our final answer as well.
So that's one of the things
that we're gonna be looking at.
Let's do one last example of combined
operations with units to show
all of it together with rounding.
So on this last example, what
we're going to be actually
looking at is this problem above.
So what we can see is that there is a
very big problem with multiple steps
in it, many different types of units.
So what we have above is 12.489
centimeters minus 4.234 centimeters times
30.72 kilograms divided by 25.5 seconds.
Oh, that's a lot.
So we gotta remember our units.
That was the one of the
big tips I put here.
So let's do the first part, which
is parentheses, so we can do
the parentheses, we can subtract
because they are the same units.
So when we do that, what we're going to
get is 8.255 centimeters times that 30.72
kilograms divided by that 25.5 seconds.
And I'm gonna leave that in
parentheses so you can kind of
remember where that came from.
Now one thing we have to do
is keep track of sig figs.
So you can see we have 1, 2,
3 sig figs for each of those
values after the decimal.
So that means that this one did not
get affected at all from our rounding.
So we're gonna cut leave it at
that point, so we know that it's
gonna be three after the decimal.
So, okay, so that's
good to know for later.
The next step is, remember that
I said that everything that is in
the denominator, in the numerator,
assume that they are in parentheses.
So we're gonna assume the top.
And the bottom are in parentheses.
So we're gonna do our order of operation
or multiplication on top first.
So when we take 8.255 times
30.72, we are going to get
253.5936 divided by 25.5 seconds.
So that would've been
the next part, right?
That would've been your multiplication.
I'm gonna write this, label those for us.
So when we do that step, what we
have to do is counter sig figs again.
So what we have is four sig figs on the
left and four sig figs on the right.
So we're still right around that
same point, still at four sig figs.
Our next portion is divide, which when
we have these two values, so we have
our four sig figs from the top number.
Then we have a total of
three sig figs on the bottom.
What this tells us is finally we have a
number that's gonna affect our sig figs.
So we are going to have three
sig figs as our final answer.
So when we carry that out,
remember we save rounding for last.
So I'm just gonna write every value
that we have on our calculator.
So we have 9.44847.
When we are doing that as well, we should
also be keeping our units in here, which
I realized mine kind of disappeared.
So on the step before centimeters and
kilograms, they multiplied together.
So they stayed.
And then we also have seconds.
So this thing is going to be
centimeters, kilograms, all over seconds.
It's this big derived unit
that we are making here.
So centimeters times.
Kilograms all over seconds.
Now, being that we said that we're going
to be rounding this to three sig figs,
so we're gonna round it right here.
This is going to equal 9.94 centimeters
times kilograms divided by seconds.
So this was a tougher problem, right?
So with these types of problems,
they can have all kinds of.
Different amounts of difficulty to
them depending on what you have to do.
Most problems are not as
tough as this last one.
So when it comes to this, hopefully
this kind of helped you see like what
you can do when it comes to rounding.
It'll help you with your homework
when you're going through many
different problems like this.
When you're doing your orders
operations, just remember, right?
Remember PDOs, remember please
excuse my dear Aunt Sally, and
remember your rounding rules.
So don't forget parentheses, then
exponents, multiply and divide.
Then addition, subtraction.
I hope this video helped you as
you try to go through all of your
future problems when it comes to
your, your chemistry homework.
All right, I'll see you soon for,
for our next video when it comes
to helping you ace chemistry.
I look forward to seeing the future.
Alright, now.
Bye now.